you diving into insurance like then why
what made you decide to do that? That
sounded like
>> all right. So
>> like actually before I was in the MLM
business we call MLM business but
something happened in the middle. So we
need we all quit from the company and
then that's basically my lowest point of
my life
>> where I was like because you know during
the prime time of the business we bought
a super nice sport cars we spend here we
max our credit cards and everything but
when things happen that's it you earn
nothing.
So you
and then after that thing happened
that's the first time I used my degree
I had no choice because I need money to
survive
>> and then I send my degree to a few
places and then
>> um I imagine that it's so difficult for
an agent themselves like I don't want to
appear like I'm pestering my client but
I'm doing the best I can.
How did you manage that? Right. Were you
worried about the perception? Whilst
your intentions may have been good, were
you worried about, oh, my clients may
think, oh, now I'm doing too much. I'm
I'm calling them way too many times. I'm
trying to convince them too hard. Was
that a difficulty that you actually
faced?
It's all come back to the right mindset.
We learn about this thing that we focus
on circle that we can control, not the
things we cannot control. like mentioned
just now uh later my client will think
that I will be pushy and everything that
is our out of our control things I
control is just do my part just keep on
approaching people telling people what's
the importance of this thing if they
want to take it then thank god because
they understand for this product if they
don't want it's okay maybe they haven't
have the awareness yet or they haven't
understand enough
>> what's the most emotional experience
you've had maybe a memorable experience
where you're like oh I am I've I've part
of the story where I have transformed a
client's life
I have this one client
she been diagnosed with this tumor
uh behind her brain and then the total
operational cost is more than 80,000
And then she is just a pl
just a pl. So that happened when I was
in my first year.
Welcome to Go Talk Studios. I'm your
host Lionel Lapidos. Here at Go Talk
Studios, we bring you real people, real
stories, real sowak.
Now, most people avoid the topic of
insurance well before they need it. And
by then, it's probably way too late or
too expensive. Today's guest has spent
13 years changing that conversation, one
family at a time.
Maria Kumang Ningan is a unit manager of
Credential and a co-founder of the Spy
Group Malaysia, a team of financial
planners that she's helped build from
the ground up since 2021 that now spans
Cuching, Miri, and Galantani. She
started when insurance was not a
respected career choice, particularly
for degree holders.
She built it anyway, and now she spends
her time growing the next generations of
leaders in this space.
>> Maria,
>> yes. Welcome to Go Talk Studio.
>> Thank you. Thank you for inviting me.
>> Hey, it feels like it's an honor to have
you here. Happy Rya.
>> Yes. Happy Rya to you.
>> Oh yeah. How have the Rya holidays been?
>> Oh my goodness.
>> Are you still celebrating?
>> Basically, we are still celebrating. You
know, like Rya is one month.
>> Well,
>> and I think today is the eighth day of
Rya. I'm not mistaken.
>> Oh, is it? I've lost track. Well, thank
you so much. Um maybe before we start
you could tell us who's Maria, where is
she from? What's her story?
>> Okay. So
I am born in Puching.
>> Yes, I'm born in Puching. So basically,
yes, I'm I'm local here. Um I studied
have few schools
in when I was in primary school. I went
to SRK Mango and then and form one I
went to SMK Paris cinema one and my form
two until form five is SMK in BU and
then I pursue my matrix in laban college
metrics labwan and then I pursue my
degree in microbiology in
university Kanga Malaysia UKM
>> micro biology Um
how how did you get to studying
microbiology?
>> Uh frankly speaking that time in my mind
I was just okay I just want to enter any
university in KL
>> you were targeting KL.
>> Yes.
>> Why? Why?
>> Why? Because I just want to get out from
Puching
>> because for the past 17 years you have
been in coaching only. So I know that if
I go out from puching I believe I will
exposed to something different
>> and learn something different as well.
>> Okay.
>> So then when you graduated with your
microbiology then did you actually work
as a microbiologist?
>> No.
>> Oh my goodness. So what happened? What
happened right after that point?
>> Okay. What happened? actually uh during
my third year in uni um I joined what
so-al multi-level marketing so that time
is when I polish my entrepreneurship
mindset so I talk to myself oh I think I
don't want to work with people I want to
build my own business yes I want to
build my own business so right after I
finished my degree I because during my
third year I already started my
business. I already built a team over
there. Yes. So after I graduate then I
came back to coaching and I built a
bigger group here in Cuching.
>> Oh my.
>> Yes. Under that specific um multi-level
marketing company.
>> Okay. Oh. Oh. Okay. So I think we're
going to get into that a little bit
later.
>> Yes. Yes. um
>> you diving into insurance
>> like then why what made you decide to do
that? That sounded like
>> All right. So
>> like actually before I was in the MLM
business, we call it MLM business, but
something happened in the middle. So we
need we all quit from the company and
then that's basically my lowest point of
my life
>> where I was like because you know during
the prime time of the business
we bought a super nice sport cars we
spend here we max our credit cards and
everything but when things happen
>> that's it you earn nothing. M
>> so you
and then after that thing happened
that's the first time I used my degree
I had no choice because I need money to
survive
>> and then I send my degree to a few
places and then um luckily there's one
college that accepted me to be their
tutor.
>> Oh wow.
>> Yes. So
uh I've been there tutoring for like
less than 24 months less than 24 months.
But during
when I was working with that college uh
my introducer and my leader in this
industry credential
>> um she already how do you say that
introduced me to this insurance industry
>> but that time I was not really like ah
insurance oh no not my cup of tea.
>> Oh really? So I rejected her and for
almost like one year plus because I I
I've seen she's been growing so so big
and then she achieved this award. She
traveled a lot and everything. So I told
to myself this is a good business. I
should give it a try.
>> Ah so you're seeing your leader making
these moves and you're like it's kind of
what I want.
>> Yes. Exactly.
>> All right. Now you mentioned two
specific challenges when you started. Um
the first being the stigma around being
an insurance agent
>> and the low financial awareness among
bum pas
>> for you which one was harder to deal
with and how did you manage to push
through that?
>> Basically at the first place I have this
wrong mindset. I feel like oh bumra they
don't they don't believe in insurance
they don't believe in insurance but
actually when I think back actually it
depends on you yourself how you set it
in your mind
>> if you think they don't believe in you
then that's it they won't believe in you
>> correct
>> but I that time I can see that this is a
very big market it's a blue ocean
>> we call blue ocean market so because not
many people especially bumutras
want to do insurance as their career. So
why not I jump and take the risk to do
this. After all, let's say if I fail
after two years, I still can use my
degree to
>> Yes. Teach your teacher or anything.
Yes. So it's it's it's no harm to to
try. So I told myself I give it two
years. If I can make it then that's it.
I will go big.
>> Oh wow.
>> So it was really the mindset. M um what
about the stigma though? I think it is
quite common, right? That um I see the
jerks online. Um oh my gosh, if your
friend is an insurance agent now,
they're going to be calling you. They
want to have Were you experiencing that?
Loser friend.
>> Yes. Yes. I did. I did. I did. Um but
you know when you have this mindset that
you really want to help people because
you know this is very good financial
tool learning and one of the reason why
our own people beingra that we still
poor in managing our financial very very
poor
>> so when something hit then we have no
money to to you know to settle all this
thing like
>> like if death happened to the young
family or if like uh hit or diagnosed by
any critical illnesses. So that's where
they need a lot of money. But looking at
this industry especially this insurance
how they help people like potential
itself is already more than 100 years in
Malaysia. It's more than 100 years.
>> Oh wow.
>> It's a very strong company. So if if
it's not a good business, I don't think
they will survive today.
>> Indeed.
>> Yes. M
>> that stigma though right especially as
an individual I think
>> right that's the one thing people know
they need it
>> yes
>> but they they create the stigma around
the agents themselves
>> agents this why I tell you before like
okay I know this is a good thing I just
keep on doing it just keep on educating
I just keep on spreading the awareness
>> because somehow sooner or later they all
need this
>> they will eventually come around
>> eventually yes because Now the people
still look in uh at insurance as a I
want this thing. It's a want thing.
>> Uh but actually insurance is a need. You
need it. It's not that you want.
>> Correct.
>> Yes.
>> So did you actually lose any friends as
a result of your career choice?
>> Lose any friends?
>> Maybe. But
I gain
1,000 times more friends.
>> Oh my goodness.
>> Yes. because um this insurance because
you meet a lot of people every day. So
that's how you meet friends basically
like one day I need to meet minimum
three person.
So you see at least like one week I need
to meet at least minimum 15 persons.
>> Okay. You know it sounds like you have a
high threshold for meeting people. You
know at some point don't you feel
fatigued having to meet so many people a
day?
>> Uh no because
it's my patient.
Yes. Because if you're passionate about
what you're doing, you don't feel fatic.
You don't feel tired. And I love meeting
people.
>> You're see you're very good at selling.
That's very clear. Very positive. Very
everything is
>> I enjoy what I'm doing. But like like
you you first time meeting you and I
enjoy talking to you.
>> So I bring that type of mindset attitude
talking to other people.
>> Oh, I'm humble. Thank you. I certainly
enjoy talking to you too. Then maybe you
could tell us then what was the lowest
point in your career?
>> The moment that maybe you kind of
thought maybe I need to reconsider this.
>> Um
let me check back. It was in my second
year I think
actually before I uh from my past
experience doing the multi-level
business actually I had a lot of I mean
a huge debt
>> huge debt. So that time I was like I
think I need to find another job and it
I want to um fast money
but when I look back okay Maria just
give yourself one more year just one
more year just hang on there just do it
uh this won't last long this won't last
long so I just keep on motivating myself
and then I just go
>> yes yes I have that thought actually But
when I see the options out there cannot
compare to this
>> because because I thought to myself I
don't want to work with people. Ah,
>> I want to have flexible job,
>> flexible time,
>> to own your own time.
>> Because when you work people, you have
to you have the 8 to5 8 to5 and then you
stuck in gym or everything. I don't want
to be in that what what do you call it
red race.
>> Correct. Correct. And I suppose that
explains now you've been in this for 13
years and that's a pretty long time.
>> I think social media has probably it's
been a game changer, right? And in your
eyes then how would you say social media
has changed the landscape for financial
planners particularly sarak
>> Sarak because you know basically
everyone has Facebook
>> Tik Tok Instagram so agents keep on
promoting their products and uh keep on
spreading awareness through all the
social media so that's why um now people
are more aware
>> so easier for us to approach them.
>> Uh they are more open.
>> They're more open.
>> So you feel it social media has actually
made it easier?
>> Yes, exactly. Made it easier.
>> Though do you wonder if is the public
more educated or are they just more
exposed? Because I think those are two
different things, right? You may be
exposed but not necessarily so educated
about it.
>> Yes, they're I I agree with you. They
are more exposed
>> but at least they have that a little bit
of how do you say that? Knowledge. M
>> so when we as a the wealth planners
financial planners
>> we that's our responsibility to make
them understand
>> uh the importance of having the right
financial planning.
>> Okay. So let's dive into that a little
bit more. Yes.
>> All right.
>> Um so a lot of people may see insurance
as an expense. All right. Not
necessarily an asset. So how then do you
approach a client who maybe has that
mindset? What do you tell them to get
them to change that?
>> Okay. Because we focus on the benefits
how this thing can help let's say today.
Okay. Linal
this insurance thing financial uh tool
actually it helps you to create um the
small money will create big money. M
>> let's say today you just put 200 ringgit
but you have 1 million coverage. If
something happened tomorrow
>> bye-bye then your family will get 1
million on the spot
by only putting 200 ringit. Can you see
that? So so insurance is a very powerful
tool to create very big money but you
just need just small portion of money
>> to create that very big fund.
as long as you do so consistently.
That's true.
>> Yes. Yes.
>> Then when it comes to myths, all right,
as in fact, myths like
>> are there what's maybe the biggest myth
you find maybe particularly among the
booming pua community when it comes to
insurance?
>> The myth insurance um it's hard to
claim,
right? A lot of people said it's hard to
claim.
>> That's a myth.
>> Yes. I hard uh I I I understand why
people say that
>> because actually it's case to case basis
case to case basis there must be a solid
reason why the case is rejected.
>> We we as an insurance company like
credential is a very big solid company
we cannot simply reject people's claim.
So there must be a black and white
rejected. M.
>> So you'd say as long as all the ducks
are in a row.
>> Mhm.
>> So you So you'd say it's a myth that
insurance companies don't make it
difficult for their clients.
>> Yes. Yes. It's a myth actually. It's a
myth. So as long as you provide all the
documents and then you have the the
right agent to help you
>> to help you then you your plan will be
very smooth.
>> Oh. So could we say that at times then
it may not necessarily be the company
itself but also not having the right
agent. M yes agents and com company we
work together and basically company is
very important because company is the
the payer you know the payer so please
choose if you want to buy insurance
please good a company is a good payer
master
>> okay
>> all right
>> then at what stage right uh maybe the
people considering okay maybe I should
get into insurance especially young
people at what stage in life should they
start actually considering maybe taking
insurance
>> prenatal plan as early as 13 weeks in
the womb.
>> 13 weeks in the womb. Oh, so before
you're even aware of life out, you
should have something.
>> Exactly. Yes. Yes. Yes. So that's why
now it's easier for us to approach
people because people also know oh
credential do have insurance like cover
the pregnancy.
>> Okay.
>> So basically everyone needs insurance.
>> I see.
>> Everyone.
>> Okay. So maybe you can walk us through
what what does a good insurance plan
look like for a family, right? Um maybe
you could tell us what should they have
and maybe in what order.
>> Basically um if you're bread winner,
bread winner, you must have a um how to
say edequate
amount of life insurance.
>> Okay,
>> which is basically we count it like 10
times of your annual income.
>> The minimum. Let's say your annual
income is 100k per year. So at least you
have like 1 million.
>> 1 million
>> is 1 million. So
>> don't should anything happen to the uh
bread winner. So the family still can
survive at least for another 10 years.
>> So you'd say that's the very first thing
to get.
>> Yes. Yes. At least. And the second thing
that people normally is a very famous
plan is the medical card itself.
Medical card. So yes everyone because of
course you cannot say that you are
healthy. Of course you you you may how
to say that take care of your diet your
sleep or everything but like accident
nobody
>> can predict that. So of course you need
a medical cut for you to go to the
private hospital because yes we do have
>> general hospital but
>> you don't want to waste your time
waiting for the years the cure
everything. M so that's why people say
if you have money you go to the private
hospital but I don't need money but I
need medical card to go to the private
hospital.
>> Indeed.
>> Okay. Then let's dive into the Aspire
Group Malaysia. Right.
>> Right. What made you and your
co-founders decide to build something
beyond just individual agents?
>> Because our vision is we want to be the
number one agency in the hearts and mind
of people in Malaysia. So we need a
group so we so that we can work together
>> like we have a group in Kuching itself
in Clantan in Miri. So even though we
are far away but we can work together
and we want to expand, we want to create
leaders in every major cities in
Malaysia. Mhm.
>> So that's our projects actually
>> our projects
>> um and come with our mission is we want
to provide the professional financial
services because you know one of the
stigma last time a lot of people said
okay those agent they will come and go
>> indeed
>> come and go. So that's why we come up
with this mission want to provide
professional financial services through
our expertise led by leaders in a
harmonious working culture. M
>> all right so that's our mission when we
want to build this
>> group
>> and you founded this in March 2021
>> and this was right in the middle of the
pandemic
>> exactly
>> I would imagine that brought about some
unique challenges why did you guys found
why did you start that right then
>> that time we can see that our group is
growing bigger
>> but we need a platform home to perform
more.
>> Uh because before this we are
independent like yes we are agents but
directed through credential but we need
a agency a group that can push us
further. M
>> uh so like our group is basically u we
call it 100% bumra group
>> so far in Malaysia itself because
bumutra we can we divided into two
>> the malays and the others
>> so basically we are the one of the
biggest womenra
>> agency in Malaysia.
>> Wow.
Did you guys starting during the
pandemic did that present a challenge or
that sounds like it was a difficult time
to actually just get anything done?
>> How do you say that?
We had that proposal before
>> one year before
>> before the pandemic actually.
>> So we hold it and then we feel like we
cannot wait too long. So we must start
>> regardless of the condition. We cannot
we cannot wait for the right moment. We
must start.
>> Wow.
>> We must start. So that's why we
>> you just decided to forge ahead.
>> Exactly.
>> And you now have six leaders right
across Kuching Miri and
>> Katan.
>> So what does that take for you to lead
these teams that are so spread apart?
That sounds difficult. Um because every
how to say every every location we have
leaders that superi supervises the the
place like Guantanam and Kuching we have
four leaders
>> like I mentioned to you just now. Our
mission is we want to work in a
harmonious working culture.
As long as we how do you say accept each
other, everyone know what is the vision,
what is the mission.
>> So it's not that hard to really work
together and then make things happen.
>> So we like
>> one language, one heart, one soul so we
can move together. Oh, so just the fact
that you guys are spread over these
locations is actually not that difficult
because of this united mission and
vision.
>> Okay,
>> we have we have zooms, we have headphone
and everything. So basically it's not a
it's not a challenge at all. We can
still always communicate.
>> It actually sounds like the fact that
you guys started during the pandemic
when all these tools were really
becoming useful now that kind of makes
it easier to work across locations.
Okay. So you did speak of your mission
and your vision. Now I wonder then what
is your vision for the Aspired Group in
the next 5 years? What do you see Aspire
Group what what will it be in the next 5
years?
>> Like I mentioned just now we just want
to be the number one
>> agency. So that is our big project and
that is our vision. So that people we
want to become the household brand. uh
think of insurance, think of spy group.
>> Okay.
>> So this passion of yours for developing
say the next generation of wealth
leaders um I wonder what that looks like
on a dayto-day because building leaders
is quite ambitious theoretically but how
do you actually build the next
generation of leaders? What do you do on
a dayto-day?
Talking about leadership, one thing that
I've learned, I summarized it this um
you must know how to lead yourself
first.
If you know how to lead yourself first,
then people will follow.
You do the right thing, then your
people, I mean your agent or teammate
also will do the right things.
So it's not that easy. It's not that
hard, but actually it's simple.
>> Simple. If you just follow,
>> so
>> so it sounds like you're you're leading
by example. You're hoping, okay, if
they're looking at exactly how I'm
operating, then
>> Exactly.
>> they have a model to follow.
>> That's impressive.
>> What about when you're recruiting then?
Um, are there any particular things
you're looking at? Skill set, is it a
mindset? How do you go about recruiting?
What do you consider?
>> When I um interview the candidates,
I will ask them, what do you know about
insurance?
And I will ask them,
do you think this thing can help you and
your family?
>> If the answer is yes, then we'll come to
the club.
As long as you have the heart to change
your life and to change to change
people's life
>> then yes you are at the right track
>> because the mindset and attitude and the
skill and tool set you can develop
later.
>> Correct.
>> Uh but you have that basic things the
fundamental thing that please come over.
Uh because basically this industry is
helping people serving people. you love
to serve people, you really have the
heart to help people, then please come
and join us.
>> Okay? You know, this is a commission
based industry, right? Um, and I think
that's probably what makes it really
tough because you're relying on income,
motivation, and confidence all tying in
together, right? Um how do you how do
you keep your people motivated in those
times particularly maybe when things are
not going for them on an individual
level
>> as a new agents basically potential they
offer us platform for you to grow
there's a scheme scheme for new agents
they say if you perform like monthly
they have monthly target
actually basically it's quite a low
target but you will get minimum at least
2,000
But like let's say if you're a fresh
graduate if you go out there you will
basically you will get like 2,000 right?
>> So here same police are offering he is
offering the new agent that scheme
>> for minimum 18 18 months. So during the
18 months not only you get that that
scheme the money from the scheme you
will get the commission as well. So you
get two things.
>> Okay. Okay. You're doing a very good job
of recruiting people. I'm almost
convinced to join you guys.
>> Come and join us.
>> Okay. I don't know if I'll do as good
job as you, but I'll try. Um, in your
bio, you you said you lead with
positivity and you operate from
gratitude. And I think what I want to
know is where do those particular values
come from? I'm guessing something to do
with some of your experiences and how do
you hold on to that particularly in
times when things are not so easy when
you're going through a very difficult
time.
>> Yes. Excuse me. Because you know I've
been through a lot been through a lot
and along the way I learned this one
thing from my pastor.
A lot of people they just feel gratitude
when they have something good in their
life.
uh but how about if they have they are
at the lowest point of their life. So
this thing changed my mind that oh
that's why you must thank God every day
whether it's sunny day or rainy day.
>> Indeed.
>> You get what I mean?
>> Because gratitude is a very powerful
uh attitude
>> that makes you feel like um how do you
say that? you're alive and then you
don't feel anxious, don't feel like
depressed, just makes you want to live
at the present moment.
>> Uh just enjoy the day, be at the present
moment. Just be gratitude of whatever
you have now.
Just focus on the thing that you have,
not the things that you don't have.
>> Oh wow. So when you're going through a
relief, say a particularly tough, let's
say month, is that what you hold on to?
Is that how you deal with it?
>> Um, come again.
>> So say if a month is particularly
difficult for you or a period of time,
maybe in work, is that what you hold on
to to get you through the month?
>> Yes. Exactly. Exactly. Exactly. Because
life is like, you know, you learn like
the ECG reading.
>> Yes. If you're alive, meaning if like
this, you're alive, right?
>> You're alive. Correct.
>> If you're dead,
>> then it's flat. Correct.
>> Yes.
>> These are very motivational words, I
must say. I just wonder because on a
practical level, right, I think that's
kind of what we like to tell ourselves,
like, oh, you know, um, I think of the
positives. I I work through the ups and
downs.
>> It's just actually implementing it
that's kind of tough. But you've been
doing this for 13 years, so I suppose
it's probably easier now to do so,
right? because because I blame that
thing because uh some of our leaders
they told us like this tough situation
won't last tough people do
>> right on okay
>> then maybe then we can look at the
different types of agents right and
what's the difference between an agent
who just sells policies and one who will
actually change say a client's life like
what's the difference between these
What's the difference with what I can
comment about this thing is you just go
back to what is their initial intention
if they come here just for the money
trust me they won't be long enough this
industry maybe just like one or two
years only but if they come here they
put their intention of helping people
then the money will come then they will
stay along this this
>> okay so it would sound as though it
comes down to fine the motivations right
of the agent themselves but
>> I think maybe that sort of what plays
into the reputation into the bad
reputation some may get right it sounds
very difficult to navigate as an agent
themselves because now some are viewed
as pushy they're commissiondriven
um they're transactional so now imagine
I as an agent maybe those are my traits
to the public, but that's just me trying
to do a good job. Then how do you then
navigate that as an agent, right?
Without appearing too pushy, but trying
to make sure you're doing a good job.
Like I mentioned to you just now,
number one, check your intention first.
Check intention.
If you do the right thing
from the beginning, then you'll be no
problem. Just do the right thing from
the beginning.
Uh you don't do any misselling. You
don't say like okay everything is
covered everything. No you must explain
everything.
You must make sure your client
understand what they why they are having
this. Don't simply come on just support
me. You cannot you cannot do that
because definitely they will support
like one or two years and then after
that they're gone. M and then so I
suppose the
again right what I'm trying to get at
here is for the agents themselves
because I think it's so easy for us to
think of the clients right and
understandably so but I imagine that
it's so difficult for an agent
themselves like I don't want to appear
like I'm pestering my client but I'm
doing the best I can
how did you manage that right were you
worried about the perception whilst your
intentions may have been good were you
worried about oh my clients may think oh
now I'm doing too much um I'm calling
them way too many times I'm trying to
convince them too hard was that a
difficulty that you actually faced
>> it's all come back to the right mindset
>> we learn about this thing that we focus
on circle that we can control not the
things we cannot control like mentioned
just now uh later my client will think
that I will be pushy and everything that
is our out of our control things I
control is just do my part just keep on
approaching people telling people what's
the importance of this thing if they
want to take it then thank God because
they understand about this product if
they don't want it's okay maybe they
haven't have the awareness yet or they
haven't understand enough
>> and eventually they'll come back to us
because they certainly
>> exactly because this game is a we call
it game this business
>> is a spiritual game.
>> Spiritual game.
>> It's all come back to us.
>> If you portray or exute the wrong
energy, the wrong vibe, your client will
feel the wrong vibe as well. But if you
come with sincere heart to to to share,
they can feel you as well.
>> Oh, powerful words. I mean, have you
considered being a pastor?
>> No.
Sounds like that might be in your line.
Um maybe you could tell us what's been
the most emotional experience you've
had, maybe a memorable experience where
you're like, "Oh, I am I've I've part of
the story where I have transformed a
client's life.
I have this one client um
she been diagnosed with this tumor
uh behind her brain and then the total
operational cost is more than 80,000
and then she is just a clock
just a clock so that happened when I was
in my first year
so That claim also make me wow this
thing really help people
>> you know that makes me go on and on
>> and then I can see the my client's face
and her families they are so grateful
that
this lady has medical card
>> so they don't have to wait at the
general hospital so she just went to the
private hospital did the treatment
straight
That
>> yes
>> is a beautiful story.
>> Yes.
>> That sounds like a motivating factor to
continue pushing, right? And that was in
your first year.
>> Yes, in my first year. And then my
training was just a just a normal like
admin stuff.
>> Wow. Now I can see why you've pushed
through for so long.
>> Yes.
Then maybe for
our audience, right, there's a young
Sarowakian.
>> They're not really sure if they want to
dive in, but they've considered it as an
insurance agent, as a financial planner.
>> I think before you dive into any
industry, right? Um, there are some
harsh truths that you probably have to
be aware of, right? Um, and a lot of
people don't aren't aware of these
things, but this is your chance to maybe
tell us what are some things they should
be aware of before they actually make
that step to dive into this career
>> because you know this career when you
see the profile of the agents most of us
are not from the we don't have the
background of um study finance
>> correct
>> uh not like all the bankers and
everything. So, but what I like about
this business, especially our company,
they provide a lot of good trainings.
They really polish us. So, even though
you know I mentioned to you that I was
studying microology.
>> Yeah.
>> I have zero about insurance
>> but they just give you trainings and
polishes and everything. So until today,
even up until today, even I'm a leader
now, still
uh keep on learning,
>> keep on going to courses, upgrading
ourselves.
>> So for those people that are considering
this career, just please come and have a
look first. If you think that is this is
not right for you, it's okay. you still
have your degree and find other job like
how I I
>> like oh but you had something to fall
back on right
>> yes
>> that doesn't sound like so much of a
harsh truth though right it sounds like
okay well you just find out you come and
find out
>> but it does sound like there's a lot of
studying involved right you it's not
really you're not just picking up
clients off the bat you're going to have
to dedicate a lot of time to Yes.
Exactly. Exactly.
>> Is there a lot of reading involved?
>> Yes. Reading trainings and everything
just like how you are working now.
>> Correct.
>> So it's it's the same. It's the same.
It's just that it's not that super rigid
because we are dealing with people's
life
>> and then we are more flexible. So that's
why you don't feel like oh we are
studying we are studying. No
>> you don't feel like that because if in
other industry you must read everything.
So, so it's so rigid. But here you can
learn from other people. You can ask
from other people. How did you approach
this guy? How did you cross this person?
How did you blah blah blah?
>> Uh we can learn from each other from
other agents that perform
>> not only from the book because the book
is just theory
>> with something else in practice.
So for you, you you're established,
you've built yourself quite an
impressive career. Maybe you would ask
what's one decision that you made, could
be personal, could be professional, that
really changed your trajectory.
I become an agent for the because I
started my journey in 2013, right?
>> And I promoted in 2022. I think it's
like nine years I've been
uh an agent for nine years and then I
promote at my 10th year
pro to my uh become manager. So when I
look back if I work with other industry
maybe I don't think I will get this same
career path that I've been dreaming of.
uh not to say about the money itself of
course because if I compare let's say if
I'm still working with my degree I don't
think I will get this type of
>> you know
you wouldn't be as
>> yes
>> financially stable
>> yes and then being with potential
because they offer a lot of contests
rewards and everything so when you work
hard you achieve your target then you
just how do I say that Just enjoy enjoy
the trip that Rachel giving to you.
>> Okay. Wonderful. We're almost wrapping
up. So maybe a few more questions. Let's
say
if free consultation for our guests, for
our audience today, if you could give
one piece of financial advice to our
audience, what would it be? Okay. So
today let's say if someone I mean a
financial planner
come and approach you please give them
one chance for them to explain to you
because you don't know maybe there might
be the angel that God is sending to you
because you don't know what happened
because you we couldn't predict what
happened in the next 5 minutes
>> correct
>> or 1 hour or one day. So just give
yourself a chance to listen first. Uh
then up to you you decide if you want to
go for that then go ahead. As long as
you give a chance to understand first
the concept of this financial planning
by using insurance.
>> Okay. Wonderful. And maybe if you'd like
this could be a chance to tell us about
maybe a plan or suite of plans that are
available that are there for our
audience to consider. Basically in
insurance we have education plan, we
have retirement plan, we have saving
plan, we have ladies and men's plan of
course we have medical card
uh we have the how do you call it MLTA
MLT
we have the um keyman business plan
uh if in Takahu you call it hiba
uh we have a lot of products that we can
offer according according to your needs.
>> Yes. According to your needs.
>> Oh, so that's quite a selection of
plans.
>> Quite a selection. Yes. Yes.
>> And
>> well, as an individual, I think I'd feel
pretty overwhelmed, but I suppose that's
where you come in and then you provide
the guidance.
>> So basically, as a person at least you
have a life insurance, critical illness
plan and medical cut. At least you have
these three basics first. Then you have
extra budget. they go for saving plan or
retirement plan.
>> Wonderful.
>> And maybe to conclude, if you could go
back and tell yourself something on day
one of this career, what would it be?
>> Day one,
>> let me think for 5 seconds.
>> With all this knowledge that you've
accumulated, right, you go back to young
Maria, day one that she's begun, what
would you tell her?
Congratulation, you made it.
>> Oh my. From on day one, like this is the
best decision you've made in your life.
>> Yes. Yes. Yes. Because you know this
business,
>> you must always put you must always feed
your mind with all the positivity.
>> You must already can foresee yourself
that you're already there.
>> That sounds like a healthy attitude to
adopt in life in general.
>> So yes, Maria, you can do it. Yes. Go
ahead. Yes. Congratulation. You made it.
Uh
>> well, on with those words. Thank you so
much, Maria. That was a very positive
message.
>> Yes.
>> Ladies and gentlemen, that was Maria. 13
years in an industry where people may
typically underestimate you. We're
building a you're building a team across
what three cities and still showing up
every single day for your clients.
That's not just a career, right? That's
a mission. And to everyone watching, if
this made you think about your own
financial plan, please share it with
someone who needs to hear it. Subscribe
for more honest conversations on Go Talk
Studios. And Maria, you know our closing
statement. I'll give you a count to
three. All right. So, we'll say this
together. One, two, three. Real people,
real stories, real saw. Until next time.
All right.
>> Bye.